<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<key ref="Promethes" document="Klopfstein-2014" lang="en">
  <title>Key to species</title>
  <couplet ref="1">
    <if>
      <and>
        Antenna orange or brown, long and slender, with 22 or more
        flagellomeres; first flagellomere more than 5 times as long as
        wide.
      </and>
      <and>
        Hind tibia orange or yellow, apex sometimes dark.
      </and>
      <and>
        Metasoma in females and often also in males marked with orange
        on at least some of tergites 2 to 5.
      </and>
    </if>
    <then>
      <ref>2</ref>
    </then>
  - <if>
      <and>
        Antenna black or sometimes brown, stouter, with 22 or fewer
        flagellomeres; first flagellomere at most 4.5 times as long as
        wide.
      </and>
      <and>
        Hind tibia white or yellow with a dark subbasal and apical
        band.
      </and>
      <and>
        Metasoma in females entirely black, in males often with yellow
        markings.
      </and>
    </if>
    <then>
      <ref>3</ref>
    </then>
  </couplet>
  <couplet ref="2">
    <if>
      <and>
        Malar space with a deep subocular groove (Fig. 21A).
      </and>
      <and>
         Scutellum yellow-marked.
      </and>
    </if>
    <then>
      <taxon>Promethes bridgmani Fitton</taxon>
    </then>
  - <if>
      <and>
        Malar space without subocular groove (Fig. 21B).
      </and>
      <and>
        Scutellum black.
      </and>
    </if>
    <then>
      <taxon>Promethes sulcator (Gravenhorst)</taxon>
    </then>
  </couplet>
  <couplet ref="3">
    <if>
      <and>
        Second metasomal tergite rugose, matt, wider than long.
      </and>
      <and>
        Mesopleuron distinctly punctate over most of its surface.
      </and>
      <and>
        Petiolar area of propodeum filled with carinulae.
      </and>
      <and>
        Females with metasoma dorsoventrally depressed to apex.
      </and>
    </if>
    <then>
      <taxon>Promethes nomininguis Dasch</taxon>
    </then>
  - <if>
      <and>
        Second metasomal tergite smooth and shining at least on apical
        half, basally with longitudinal wrinkles, longer than wide.
      </and>
      <and>
        Mesopleuron with punctures weak, distinct at most on lower
        half.
      </and>
      <and>
        Petiolar area of propodeum mostly smooth, with carinulae
        restricted to its margins.
      </and>
      <and>
        Females with metasoma laterally compressed.
      </and>
    </if>
    <then>
      <ref>4</ref>
    </then>
  </couplet>
  <couplet ref="4">
    <if>
      <and>
        Scutellum with a large yellow blotch covering most of its
        surface.
      </and>
      <and>
        Mesoscutum with large yellow shoulder marks which usually
        expand over notauli.
      </and>
      <and>
        Basal area of propodeum usually more than 2.5 times wider than
        long, with apical carina often partly reduced (Fig. 22A).
      </and>
    </if>
    <then>
      <taxon>Promethes nigriventris (Thomson)</taxon>
    </then>
  - <if>
      <and>
        Scutellum usually black but sometimes marked with yellow on
        anterior part, especially in males.
      </and>
      <and>
        Mesoscutum without or at most with small yellow shoulder marks
        which do not expand over notauli.
      </and>
      <and>
        Basal area of propodeum usually less than 2 times wider than
        long, with apical carina strong (Fig. 22B).
      </and>
    </if>
    <then>
      <taxon>Promethes melanaspis (Thomson)</taxon>
    </then>
  </couplet>
</key>
