<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<key ref="Promethes" document="Klopfstein-2014" lang="en">
  <title>Key to species</title>
  <couplets type="">
    <couplet ref="1">
      <lead>
        <character>
          Antenna orange or brown, long and slender, with 22 or more
          flagellomeres; first flagellomere more than 5 times as long
          as wide. Hind tibia orange or yellow, apex sometimes
          dark. Metasoma in females and often also in males marked
          with orange on at least some of tergites 2 to 5.
        </character>
        <pass>2</pass>
      </lead>-
      <lead>
        <character>
          Antenna black or sometimes brown, stouter, with 22 or fewer
          flagellomeres; first flagellomere at most 4.5 times as long
          as wide. Hind tibia white or yellow with a dark subbasal and
          apical band. Metasoma in females entirely black, in males
          often with yellow markings.
        </character>
        <pass>3</pass>
      </lead>
    </couplet>
    <couplet ref="2">
      <lead>
        <character>
          Malar space with a deep subocular groove
          (Fig. 21A). Scutellum yellow-marked.
        </character>
        <taxon>Promethes bridgmani Fitton</taxon>
      </lead>
      <lead>-
        <character>
          Malar space without subocular groove (Fig. 21B). Scutellum
          black.
        </character>
        <taxon>Promethes sulcator (Gravenhorst)</taxon>
      </lead>
    </couplet>
    <couplet ref="3">
      <lead>
        <character>
          Second metasomal tergite rugose, matt, wider than
          long. Mesopleuron distinctly punctate over most of its
          surface. Petiolar area of propodeum filled with
          carinulae. Females with metasoma dorsoventrally depressed to
          apex.
        </character>
        <taxon>Promethes nomininguis Dasch</taxon>
      </lead>
      <lead>-
        <character>
          Second metasomal tergite smooth and shining at least on
          apical half, basally with longitudinal wrinkles, longer than
          wide. Mesopleuron with punctures weak, distinct at most on
          lower half. Petiolar area of propodeum mostly smooth, with
          carinulae restricted to its margins. Females with metasoma
          laterally compressed.
        </character>
        <pass>4</pass>
      </lead>
    </couplet>
    <couplet ref="4">
      <lead>
        <character>
          Scutellum with a large yellow blotch covering most of its
          surface. Mesoscutum with large yellow shoulder marks which
          usually expand over notauli. Basal area of propodeum usually
          more than 2.5 times wider than long, with apical carina
          often partly reduced (Fig. 22A).
        </character>
        <taxon>Promethes nigriventris (Thomson)</taxon>
      </lead>
      <lead>-
        <character>
          Scutellum usually black but sometimes marked with yellow on
          anterior part, especially in males. Mesoscutum without or at
          most with small yellow shoulder marks which do not expand
          over notauli. Basal area of propodeum usually less than 2
          times wider than long, with apical carina strong (Fig. 22B).
        </character>
        <taxon>Promethes melanaspis (Thomson)</taxon>
      </lead>
    </couplet>
  </couplets>
</key>
